so we got a question this morning
i was wondering if you could
answer it again
and the question is what is the
difference between chanda and tanha chanda being chanda being
desire being craving
yeah so the difference is that chanda
chanda
as a desire as a as a form of zeal
interest can
can
well can be either wholesome or
unwholesome so if you have if you have a desire to
so if you have if you have a desire to
or
that is under chandaraga
that is not that it's not a wholesome
desire but then if you wanna if you want to be
but then if you wanna if you want to be
free from sensuality say you started and
you began to understand
the satisfaction of it and so on then
you can actually have a desire
to be free from it to be free from
sensuality and sensual desire so it's
still a form of desire
that can now make you actually want to
practice the dharma and sense restraint
and so on so that's also desire
but it's a desire that can actually
eventually result in freedom from desire
freedom from sensual desire freedom from
from the
desire for pleasures and so on
so chanda is not uh
in itself
bad no good it's really
no good it's really
um it depends where you direct it
so that's why the
those like types of striving that the
winner describes in the suttas you know
that's all based on desire desire for
abandoning the unwholesome states and
desire for increasing the wholesome
states um so it's not a it's not a question of
um so it's not a it's not a question of
not having desires
when you begin to practice
it's really about having the desires
that are directed at development of
wholesomeness and skillfulness
that that will then result in
diminishing of unwholesome and
unwholesome desires and everything else
and then when you're completely free
from any any desire towards sensuality
and so on
you will also lose the desire towards
wholesomeness because that is now what
you are so you don't need to have a
desire to develop wholesomeness once you
develop the wholesomeness
so that's how desire
directed rightly can result in freedom
from desire altogether freedom from
chanda altogether
so you could say that the arahant the
one accomplished fully accomplished the
buddha has no has no
desire
yeah he is free from chandra completely
yeah exactly
abandoning desire is not a matter of
choice abandoning of desire it's a matter of
abandoning of desire it's a matter of
directing desire
towards the behavior
of a certain kind i gradual training
they will then remove any basis for
perpetration of desire later on
so in other words
you become aware of your illness
you need to have a desire to be cured
because that desire will make you seek
for uh look out look for a doctor
find the right medicine and then sustain
the application of the medicine on the
basis of desire for health
and then once you're cured
and healed and there is absolutely no
more no not even like the slightest
traces of your illness you will have no
more desire left to be cured because
you're cured
but if while you're real
you think that okay so being free from
illness means no desire thus i will have
no desire that just will prevent you
from actually curing yourself
so you want to direct the desire rightly
on account of which you will start
making the right effort a person cannot
distinguish in the beginning desire what
is this desire what is health desires
bad desire is bad
um
so
that's why you need to start with a
sense of strength as we always say
but you don't want to be trying to not
have desires
you want to be trying to see where your
desires are directed at
and if it's a desire for physical
pleasures uh you know of the lustful kind where we
uh you know of the lustful kind where we
spoke before the one that incite the
lust and overwhelm the mind and make you
get out of the chair as we as you gave
the simile
that's the desire you should not
cultivate that's desire you should
abandon not welcome
not entertain
endure until it passes without acting
out of
so the question of say for example
anagami who is free from central desire
he's not free from chanda
he's free from chanda to words to sense
objects of pleasures and so on so in
other words freedom from sensuality
doesn't mean absence of chandra of any
kind it means loss of interest loss of
zeal for the central type of pleasure
why well because the gratification has
been fully understood the danger has
been fully understood and the escape has
been fully understood
so it's not that anagami or an arahant
have no concept anymore of what physical
pleasure would feel like it's they have
no interest in it anymore on the level
of their mind and intent and thought
so so they're absolutely free from any
zeal that person not free from sensuality
that person not free from sensuality
would otherwise have and you could see
that you have a you would have like a
person will have a central thought and
that is immediate like quite a
strong depending on how how much mind
development you have sort of uh engaged
with but there is there will be an
inclination towards it there will be
like this this welcoming of that
prospect even if you practice sense restraint
even if you practice sense restraint
so that's why you are not free from
centrality because of that mental
delight chanda desire
zeal whatever you want to translate it
so one and that can only be abandoned
through seeing the danger of that which
you're delighting towards that which
you're because if you're you know you
will not have an interest anymore in
ingesting poison if you understood the
deadliness of the poison
so the texture of it hasn't changed the
physical contact pleasure of a
pleasurable kind hasn't changed
but your understanding now of seeing it
as a poison that has changed to so you
have absolutely no zeal towards any
towards that kind of pleasure whatsoever
you have no interest in it that's
you know a lot of people can say well i
understand that sensuality is bad i
understand that i get that i get it i've
reflected on the dangers yet i'm still
attracted yeah so the buddha said that
for as long as you are not you for as
long as you haven't fully
understood the gratification
fully understood the danger and fully
understood the escape you should not
claim that you understood sensuality
because if you do means you're
contradicting yourself because if you
fully did understand these three aspects
there will be no chanda to work
sensuality left they will be chanda
toward renunciation
towards seclusion towards further
abandonment and that chant is fine
and that chant is fine
because it will make you make
more of the effort
so yes a person will inevitably think
here i understand the battle of
sensuality okay fine
ask yourself then the next question so
am i free from any form of delight
welcoming zeal interest curiosity even
zeal interest curiosity even
towards
pleasures that come on the kind of
object of the senses that are inducive
of last and so on
no i don't think i'm free of that or i'm
not sure if i'm free of that means
you're not free of that means don't
think you understood it
it means make more effort you nobody
denies that you that you will have some
insight or some degree of insight into
sensuality want to start restraining and
looking but
don't think that's the freedom up until
you know oh i am free i don't want this
this is truly something i have no
interest in anymore quite the opposite
like you know you might spend most of
the time of your day not having interest
but are you still liable to have
interest towards centrality if so you're
not outside of the domain of that karma
kamabava and kamachanda
so you always want to look on that level
of liability oh but am i liable to
become careless and interested in this
again maybe well there you go not free from
maybe well there you go not free from
doubt in regard to it not free from it
so you you want to really abandon that
zeal towards the objects of your senses
and that's freedom from kamachandra
so as as for tanha if it comes down to
downhill now that's it's it's subtle
tangha is sort of on a different level
so chanda is kind of an active thing
the you either carelessly engage with on
account of your past behavior that
hasn't been restrained or something you
can cultivate as would you say he
generates the desire so you reflect why
it's good to be cured but it's good to
make the effort where it's good to
practice gradual training where it's
good to be virtuous and sense restraint
and because of those values you reflect
upon you will generate a desire to do it
uh tanha it's more on an immediate level
of basically
your attitude towards you your present
enduring feeling whatever that is and
that attitude is always rooted in
resistance so if if there is like um
so if if there is like um
tanha for pleasure
craving for pleasure
that is rooted in you resisting
the current feeling which you know is
not necessarily unpleasant
but it's not sufficient
so the pleasure it's not sufficient
which is why you crave for more pleasure
which means in other words it's painful
any resistance is unpleasant
so if you resist
it with the mind of resistance if you
experience pleasure you will by default
resist it because by default you want
more of it by default
with the mind not free from tanha you
experience uh pain by default you're
resisting it
because you don't want any of it
you want it completely to go away
so with the mind not free from tanha you
experience a neutral feeling
say you will automatically resist it
towards oblivion towards ignorance
towards turning away from it because you
don't understand it
so tanha practically speaking is always
that resistance
on the level of what you're currently
feeling even if you're feeling pleasure you
even if you're feeling pleasure you
still resist absolutely absolutely
that's why if you're not free from tanha
every pleasure will be underlined by
craving for more and yeah and
exactly and so play as i said presence
of resistance means dukkha
and i said that before presence of tanha
means dukkha dukkha means downhill to
the extent of the pleasure that you can
actually get
so if there is still tanha there means
there is still resistance
um to whatever is there for you at the
time and that's why you suffer not because of
and that's why you suffer not because of
what's there for you at the time
and why do you like why would you be um
resisting so why would you
so why would you
why is it that you are not contented
with you know you know
some
agreeable feeling that is present why is
it that by default the mind wants more
of it
it's because of the the holding of the
view in regard to what pleasure is what
sensuality is what gratification is
where the value is
and that's why uh sensuality is a form
of upadhana it's a form of assumption
it's a form of a view
it's not a you know physical experience
of pleasure or not it's basically the
value that you have mentally that you
are called through basically
you know throughout your day day-to-day
existence yes so the assumption is that
pleasure is uh
well the assumption is that there is no
first first there's no first point that
you were not attracted to centrality and
then you began
you start by already being attracted
which means the assumption is that
the pleasure is over there
and the reason that assumption exists is
because you haven't undone you haven't
removed it that's that's the sole reason
that's why you have to contemplate the
danger of your view that pleasure is
there not not gratifying it not
welcoming it not delighting in it
and then the danger of where you think
pleasure is will become apparent
and then you would have lost the
assumption of where the pleasure is
and then you will have stopped resisting
whatever you're feeling currently
certainly on account of pleasant feeling
you wouldn't be craving for more
pleasure because the only reason you
crave for more pleasure is because you
keep assuming pleasure to be out there
and that is always always underlined by
craving for more
unsatisfactory exactly and same then you
will stop resisting by removing that
resistance towards
insufficiency of pleasure so to speak
which is your view
it's never quite enough
you will also stop resisting the
disagreeability of it which means
disagreeability of anything else
you will not resist it as much let's say
like that
so when unpleasant feeling is manifested
you will not by default trying to get
rid of it
so that's what tanha is it's that
resistance to what's being felt
central pleasure is felt unpleasantly
that's where you want to you know
seek the the the outcome that you that's
why i want to gratify your senses
because non-gratified senses hurt
so you resist the pain or your
resistance is the pain
because if you stop resisting the
non-gratified senses
they'll stop hurting
but you don't see that the pain is on
your resistance level you think the pain
is because there is no gratification of
the senses so i better go out and seek
the gratification and that's where you
keep perpetuating that mistake that you
yourself are living
so first you need to stop seeking out
the gratification of the senses
so that your resistance to the
non-gratifying senses becomes apparent
as the cause of pain
and then you realize oh i stopped
resisting it stops hurting
gratifying senses becomes redundant the
only reason you were gratifying it is
because it was hurting
beforehand and you were mistakenly thinking the
and you were mistakenly thinking the
lack of gratification is what was
hurting so seeking gratification will remove the
so seeking gratification will remove the
pain no resistance of non-gratified
senses that's what's hurting that's the
patient we spoke about the natural
fatigue of your senses
that you were resisting
you know habit resistance well yeah the
view of resistance
then habit perpetuates the view
but the habit's there because of the
view you still think the pain that
you're experiencing is because of that
not because of your resistance to to
pretty much to the pain you're
experiencing
that's what that view is important to
you that's why without the right view
yeah yeah
craving that's the problem
yeah and that's why like craving um
that resistance
results in
that's why it's beginningless it's a
vicious circle there's no beginning it's
not you are pure then you develop tanha
then you develop upadhana no no
you start already infected perverted
mistaken confused
assumed corruption is beginningless but that's
corruption is beginningless but that's
why if you understand it if you approach
it it cannot it's irreversible
so once you remove that protruder's
assumption and
that's been feeding the craving and
craving that's been feeding the
assumption once you fully approve that
it cannot take place again because he
was never supposed to be there to begin
with it was just a vicious circle
it was just a vicious circle
perpetuating itself